Hello and welcome to yet another gate layout
Walkthrough for computer architecture for
Everybody. In this we're going to play with
Several of the circuits, the counter and the
Single instruction. So if you go back and you
Take a look at the at the counter. I'm going
To build one and then I'm going to actually load
It. So we're just going to do a three-bit adder.
Put the three-bit adder in the middle here. And
So the adder takes the one two and four one two
And four as a and b and then produces a sum.
Right? So if I just take an input of one
And another input over here of one and I hook
The input to the one input and then I hook the
In the other one to the output and then I change
This and so this is going to if I have one plus
One is two. So this is a weird layout here
But this is 0 + one is should be one. Okay. So,
I had to toggle that a little bit.
Dragging it around confused it. So,
There you go. So, the idea here is we're going
To make a counter. And we're going to make a
Counter by creating a clocked circuit. So, let me
Delete this input. Delete this input. So, this is
An adder. Whatever we present as its input, it's
Going to sum them together 0 through 7, produce
The output, and tell us what the output is. And
Then we're going to make a three-bit latch. And
I'll take the output. The latch is like a little
Register. So that the register is it takes its
Inputs. It ignores its inputs until you put a one
At the clock. Let's go put a put a clock here.
So
When the clock is one, the inputs are
Being copied to the outputs. Okay? And so,
, let's do this. Let's make an input over here.
It's like a bunch of
Flip-flops output over here.
Okay. So, the so the current so the current state
Of the latch, what's stored in the register is a
Value of one. And we can change this all day
Long and it's ignoring it. That's just like a
Flip-flop. It's just like a JK flip-flop. This
Is a series of JK flip-flops in here. Flip on
And off. And then if we want to tell this register
To latch in its input values, we can say do that.
And then it latches in its input values. And then
When the clock goes low again, then it copies the
Output values. So now the internal state is zero.
So the outputs are zero because the clock is low.
So if I again now I can change this and nothing
Changes because it's a latch. And then I say,
"Oh, let the clock go high." Copies it in. Then
The clock goes low and it copies it out. Okay.
So let's go ahead and build a simple counter
Where we're just going to take a value and
Store it in this register. Okay. So now we got
The register. It's it's still got a one in it.
So, we're going to take this and we're going to
Connect the sum values to the input values of the
Latch. And this is a situation where those little
Waypoints can be really helpful. So, I'm going
To drag that one there. Connect this one to this
One. Connect the two values. This second bit,
Then make a waypoint. You got to double click
To make a waypoint. So we can make a waypoint
And then connect the four values to the latch
And double click to make a waypoint. Then pull
This out to make it so that you could see
It. So all I did is I connected the corresponding
Outputs of the adder to the input of the latch
Because we're going to take and then we're going
To take the output of the latch and connect it
To the input of the of the adder. Now, the thing
That's going to make this work so it doesn't just
Explode and start on fire is this clock
Circuit. Okay? So, I'm going to put an input on
The clock circuit. I'm going to set that to zero.
Okay? So, as long as the clock circuit is zero,
The current state of the latch is being copied
To the output values. And then what I'm going to
Do is I'm going to make this add one every time.
So I'm have an I'll just take an input and connect
It to the one value of the B operand of the
Adder. Okay. Okay. Let's make this look prettier
By putting a waypoint in. Okay. There we go. Look
How pretty that is. Way point. Nice. Let's make a
Put a waypoint here while we're at it to make it
Pretty. Okay. Look at that. It's a pretty little
Clock. Okay. So now this is a zero, but I want
To turn this to a one. Okay. Okay. And so what
Happens now is we are being presented with a one
On the A inputs the number one not a one
0 and a one and the B inputs. So the adder is
Continuously computing. So think of this as three
Full adders. Okay. It's continuously computing and
It's continuously presenting this two which is 0 1
0. It's presenting two at the inputs to the latch.
But because the latch currently has a clock of
Zero, we are not copying it. So what'll happen
Here is when we hit the clock goes to one, we will
See that the two is copied from the adder to the
Latch, but the two is not copied to the outputs
Of the latch and therefore to the inputs of the
Adder until the clock goes low again. Okay, so
Now the clock went low. So now the two
Is being presented on the inputs of the adder
And the plus one and so we get three. So if I
Just start clicking this clock off and on. Now
Remember it only it copies when it goes to one
It copies from the adder to the latch and if when
It goes to zero it copies from the latch back to
The adder. Otherwise it would just it would just
Go and we and the timing would be very weird
At that point. So this is a clocked circuit and
These registers inside CPUs tend to be clocked and
So we'll do this but let's just add a clock to it
So that we don't have to keep clicking. So let's
Take a look at this clock component and hook up
An output to it. And so the clock come on hook up
A happy little output. There we go. Okay. So the
Clock is currently off and it's producing a one.
So, I'm going to click on the clock to turn it
On. So, now it's giving high low. And you'll see
That every second the clock is going from high
To low to high to low to high to low. And so,
What I'm going to do is I'm going to delete this
Little manual clock that I put in. Goodbye. And
Delete this little output. Goodbye. And now I'm
Going to connect the high value to the clock value
On the latch. And let's go ahead and put a little
Waypoint in here to make it a little prettier.
You can drag these waypoints quite nicely. If
Anybody wants to grab the source to this and
Give me a better routing algorithm, I would
Greatly appreciate it. And so now what we're
Seeing here is this clock is going high to low
Here. Let's let's go ahead and put a little
Output here so we can watch what's going on a
Little better. Connect the high to the output.
So you can see the clock is going from 0 to
One to 0 to one. And every time it goes to one,
It copies into the latch. And then every time
It goes to zero, it copies from the latch to the
Adder and ignores. But the thing that makes
This work is like the six is being ignored until
The clock goes high. So we now have a little
Counter that's counting up to seven and then
Resetting itself. You see it says
Overflow. That's cuz when you add 7 + one,
It's zero overflow. That's when you
Carry out of the top full adder.
Okay. So, we just made a simple counter that goes
From 0 through 7 and counts up seconds. And so,
You could think of this as like a
A little clock. I think I might be
Able to put for fun a little Nixie. Let's
See if I can make a Nixie work here. So,
Here's a Nixie tube. And I think that I can
Copy this. This is going to look ugly. I'll
Just copy them here. Let's copy
The Nixie there. Copy. It's still running.
And I'm just taking the one, two, and the four
Values and copying them from the sum output.
There we go. Now, all we did is Come on, Nixie.
Move. Okay. So, the Nixie is just keeping track
Of what's going here. We could actually put a
Nixie in between here so you could see it. But
It just the Nixie outputs seven and seven. The
Adder tells us what its current output value
Is. and the latch tells us, but you can actually
Take the Nixie and use it to copy things. But it's
Pretty and it's really pretty darn awesome.
So,, so that was a counter example. So,
I hope you found this walkthrough useful and I
Hope that you can construct your own counter. Now,
I'll just say I got a cheat code in here. Okay?
So, if you really want to, you can just in you
Can load a counter. I stored a counter inside of
It. And so, there goes a counter. The clock's off.
It's got everything we just said. It's got all
The stuff connected. It's a little prettier than
The one I just drew, but I'll turn it on. And
It's starting. It's just counting every second,
Right? And the actual data here is the data in the
Latch. And that would be the thing that you would
Be to seeing if you were building like a digital
Wristwatch or something like that. Okay. So again,
Thanks for listening. I hope
You found this walkthrough useful.